W.P.A. California Folk Music Project collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Finding Aid (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Subseries II: Administrative Materials related to California WPA Project
      - Final Report of the California Folk Music Project Submitted to WPA (Box-folder 2/13)
        Statement of Accomplishment for O.P. 65-1-08-62, Unit A-25, Area Unit Serial No. 0803-1659, "A Study of California Folk Music," sponsored by the Department of Music of the University of California, Work Projects Administration, State of California, Northern District, Area No. 8, Alameda County, Berkeley, California, January, 1940. 88 pages
    - Subseries III: Field notes
      - Yellow Song Checklist: "E" (English Language) Listing, 73 pages (Box-folder 2/14)
        List of Recordings made by Sidney Robertson in California 1938-1940 arranged alphabetically by performer. Yellow and white typewritten pages, some originals, listing English-language songs recorded as part of the California Folk Music Project. Organized alphabetically by last name of performer. Includes dates and locations of performances, collector's disc number with E, indicating "English-language" songs, instrumentation, occasional background commentary on the performers and performances, location where recorded, and, at times, comments regarding quality of sound recordings.
      - Yellow Song Checklist: "E" (English Language) Listing, 73 pages (Box-folder 2/15)
        List of recordings made by Sidney Robertson in California 1938-1940 arranged alphabetically by performer. (photocopy)
      - Yellow Song Checklist: "M" (Minority) Listing, Armenian to Mexican (1/2), 103 pages (Box-folder 2/16)
        List of foreign language recordings made by Sidney Robertson in California, 1938-1940. Yellow and white typewritten pages, some originals, listing non-English language songs recorded as part of the California Folk Music Project. Organized alphabetically by cultural group. Includes dates and locations of performances, collector's disc number with M, indicating "minority," instrumentation, occasional background commentary on the performers and performances, location where recorded, and, at times, comments regarding quality of sound recordings. n.d.
      - Yellow Song Checklist: "M" (Minority) Listing, Norwegian to Spanish (2/2), 103 pages (Box-folder 2/17)
        List of foreign language recordings made by Sidney Robertson in California, 1938–1940. Yellow and white typewritten pages, some originals, listing non-English language songs recorded as part of the California Folk Music Project. Organized alphabetically by cultural group. Includes dates and locations of performances, collector's disc number with M, indicating "minority," instrumentation, occasional background commentary on the performers and performances, location where recorded, and, at times, comments regarding quality of sound recordings. n.d.
      - Yellow Song Checklist: "M" (Minority) Listing, Armenian to Mexican, 103 pages (Box-folder 2/18)
        List of foreign language recordings made by Sidney Robertson in California, 1938-1940 (photocopy).
      - WPA Field Reports, 1938-11-25 to 1939-11-20, 38 pages (Box-folder 2/19)
        Field reports submitted to the Northern California WPA Office for Folk Music Project 10482-A25, November 25, 1938-November 25, 1939
      - California Folk Music Project miscellany (Box-folder 2/20)
      - George Vinton Graham field materials (Box-folder 3/21)
      - Dust jackets, "E" [English] and "M" [minority] language (original) (Box-folder 3/22)
      - Dust jackets, "E" [English Language] (Box-folder 3/23)
      - Dust jackets, "M" [Minority Language] (Box-folder 3/24)
    - Subseries IV: Song Indexes and Transcriptions
      - Song Indexes, English and Minority Language (Box-folder 3/25)
      - English-language songs beginning with "A" (Box-folder 3/26)
      - English-language songs beginning with "B" (Box-folder 3/27)
      - English-language songs beginning with "C" (Box-folder 3/28)
      - English-language songs beginning with "D" and "E" (Box-folder 3/29)
      - English-language songs beginning with "F" (Box-folder 3/30)
      - English-language songs beginning with "G" (Box-folder 3/31)
      - English-language songs beginning with "H" (Box-folder 3/32)
      - English-language songs beginning with "I" (Box-folder 3/33)
      - English-language songs beginning with "J" and "K" (Box-folder 3/34)
      - English-language songs beginning with "L" (Box-folder 4/35)
      - English-language songs beginning with "M" (Box-folder 4/36)
      - English-language songs beginning with "N" and "O" (Box-folder 4/37)
      - English-language songs beginning with "P," "Q," and "R" (Box-folder 4/38)
      - English-language songs beginning with "S" (Box-folder 4/39)
      - English-language songs beginning with "T" (Box-folder 4/40)
      - English-language songs beginning with "U," "V," and "W" (Box-folder 4/41)
      - English-language songs beginning with "Y" (Box-folder 4/42)
      - Lists of Portuguese-language song titles, n.d., 4 pages with duplicate copy (Box-folder 4/43)
        With English translations, arranged alphabetically by title. Folder 43 (A -F) and Folder 44 (H-V) include musical transcriptions of Portuguese-language songs with lyrics, a translation of the lyrics into English and, at times, notes on these songs from the Azores that were recorded for the California collection, indexed, organized, and translated by WPA California Folk Music Project worker and performer Alice Lemos Avila.
      - Portuguese-language songs beginning with "A," "B," "E," and "F," n.d. (original) (Box-folder 4/44)
      - Portuguese-language songs beginning with "H"-"V" (original) (Box-folder 4/45)
      - Portuguese songs beginning with "A"-"V" (photocopy) (Box-folder 4/46)
      - Spanish-language songs sung by Jessie De Soto, n.d. (original), 6 pages (Box-folder 4/47)
      - English Language "A-T", 6 pages (Box-folder 5/48)
        English-language California song and poem research from printed sources for texts beginning in "A" through "T," n.d. Arranged in alphabetical order by first letter of title or first line.
      - English Language, Gold Rush Songs, n.d. (Box-folder 5/49)
        This folder includes background information on and published lyrics of Gold Rush songs copied by California WPA workers from an unidentified book at the UC Library in Berkeley. Songs, in the order in which they were prepared by the WPA staff.
      - Portuguese Language "C-V" (Box-folder 5/50)
        Portuguese-language songs arranged in alphabetical order, beginning with first letter.
      - Portuguese Language, Five Folk Dances of the Azores, 10 pages plus photocopy of same (Box-folder 5/51)
        Folk Songs and Dances from the Azores, set down by Alice Avila in Berkeley in 1938-9. Copied and translated from Portuguese by Alice Lemos Avila with notes and transcriptions from the publication entitled Portucale. Includes notes for the following songs, with lyrics and musical transcription listed by first line.
      - Spanish-language songs and their English-language translation from printed sources, n.d., 3 pages (Box-folder 5/52)
    - Subseries V: Research products by WPA staff
      - Articles in San Francisco Chronicle (1938) by Sidney Robertson Cowell (Box-folder 5/53)
        "The Songs of a Nation Collect a Forgotten Claim" and "The Spirit of a Generation Reflected in Folk Songs" by Sidney Robertson in two parts about her work collecting folk songs in California for the WPA. Published in the "This World" section, on September 4, 1938, p. 26, and September 14, 1938, p. 22.
      - Portuguese Citizens of California (original, 1939)., 58 pages (Box-folder 5/54)
        Original handwritten report in spiral notebook written by WPA California Folk Music Project worker Carmen Mell to describe the historical, cultural, and musical life of the Portuguese in California, 1939. Includes letter from Carmen Mell to Sidney Robertson that accompanied the report when it was completed. (3 pages)
      - Portuguese Citizens of California by Carmen Mell (1939) (photocopy) (Box-folder 5/55)
      - Article in California Folklore Quarterly (1942) by Sidney Robertson Cowell (Box-folder 5/56)
        3 copies of "The Recording of Folk Music in California" by Sidney Robertson. Vol. 1, No. 1, January 1942, pp. 7-23.
      - Outline for book tentatively called "Folksong in California," July 1954., 24 pages (Box-folder 5/57)
        24-page typewritten and handwritten manuscript prepared by Sidney Robertson Cowell, July 1954. Research products inspired by the WPA California Folk Music Project.
      - Published articles (Box-folder 5/58)
        Articles written about Sidney Robertson, the WPA California Folk Music Project in 1938-1940, and reviews of Sidney Robertson and Eleanora Black's compilation entitled The Gold Rush Song Book, published in 1940.
      - Catalog cards (Box-folder 5/59)
        19 catalog cards created according to guidelines and procedures of the Library of Congress, as examples for the WPA California Folk Music Project staff. The actual catalog cards prepared by project staff for the field recordings of the CFMP became part of the Archive of Folk Culture's item-level shelflist card file created by other WPA staff working in the Library in the late 1930s and early 1940s located in the Folklife Reading Room.
      - Dust jackets, "E" [English-language] (Box 7)
      - Dust jackets, "M" [minority, 1-70] (Box 8)
      - Dust jackets, "M" [minority, 71-104] (Box 9)
        The CFMP selections included here (folders 25 and up) are often annotated by an E (English-language) or M (minority) disk number, the original numbers that Robertson assigned to the recordings she made for the WPA project. The term "version" here is used to cover both true variants of a song and draft copies of transcriptions in several stages of preparation (as was frequently done by WPA staff for this collection). For Folders 24-45, see Appendix C for song titles.
- Series II: Sound Recordings
  - AFS 3342-3377; AFS 3809-3860; AFS 4194-4287
    Original field recordings made by Robertson between 1938-1940 on 12-inch acetate disks and labeled E 1-90 [English-language recordings] and M 1-109 ["Minority" or foreign-language recordings]. Arranged numerically by AFS numbers in the order in which they were received by the Archive of Folk Culture. Some of the original field recordings were sent to the Folk Archive during the project in 1939; the rest were brought in during 1940 by Robertson.
- Series III: Graphic Images
  - Subseries I: Scale drawings and sketches of musical instruments
    - Microfilm (copy) From UC Berkeley Music Library (Box-folder 5/60)
      Two duplicate rolls of microfilm copied from the University of California, Berkeley, Music Library's California Folk Music Project Collection. Includes images representing 85 preliminary sketches of the musical instruments made originally on butcher-block paper and 40 mechanical scale drawings made by WPA staff. Includes sketches of the Spanish guitar or Sonora not included below.
    - Index to scale drawings and sketches of instruments (Box-folder 6/61)
      Typewritten listing of drawings and sketches of musical instruments in collection with handwritten annotations. Undated.
    - Scale drawings and sketches of instruments (photocopies) (Box-folder 6/62)
      Photocopies of scale drawings taken from microfilm in the collection.
    - Scale drawings and sketches of instruments (photostats) (Box-folder 6/63)
      Photostats of mechanical drawings of eight musical instruments.
  - Subseries II: Photographs
    - P001-P170 (copies) (Box-folder 6/64-115)
      Duplicate photographic prints, copy negatives for photoduplication purposes, and photocopies of photographic prints.
    - P001-P170 (original) (Box-folder Binder 1)
      170 black and white photographic prints of various sizes photographed by Sidney Robertson, T.H. Hall, and possibly other WPA workers. Includes photos of WPA personnel at work, performers, sometimes with instruments, and of instruments.
Appendix A: Places Where Field Documentation was Conducted
Alameda (Calif.)
Belvedere (Calif.)
Berkeley (Calif.)
Camino (Calif.)
Carmel (Calif.)
Central Valley (Calif.) [formerly called Boomtown, near the Shasta Dam]
Clements (Calif.)
Columbia (Calif.)
Concord (Calif.)
Fowler (Calif.)
Fresno (Calif.)
Groveland (Calif.)
Hollywood (Los Angeles, Calif.)
Lotus (Calif.)
Martinez (Calif.)
Monterey (Calif.)
Mountain View (Calif.)
Oakland (Calif.)
Ortonville (Iowa)
Pacific Grove (Calif.)
Pala (Calif.)
Palo Alto (Calif.)
Pine Grove (Amador County, Calif.)
Pittsburg (Calif.)
Richmond (Calif.)
San Francisco (Calif.)
San Jose (Calif.)
San Mateo (Calif.)
Santa Barbara (Calif.)
Shasta Lake Region (Calif.)
Springfield (Mo.)
Turlock (Calif.)
Woodside (Calif.)
Appendix B: Musical Instruments Documented in Collection
Banjo
Blul Blul, blur
Celtic harp Irish bardic harp
Cimbalom Cembalomp
Clarinet
Ḍaph Defs, deff, def
Dulcimer
Dümbelek Dumbeg
Dvorgrle Dvogrla
English guitar Guitarra portuguesa, Portuguese guitar
Guitar
Gusle Gusla
Hardanger fiddle
Harmonica
Harp-lute Swedish lute, double guitar
Hawaiian guitar
Kamānche Kemancha
Lirica
Mandolin
Miŝnice Mjersnice
Oud Oude
Piano
Qānūn (Musical instrument) Kanoon
San xian San hsien
Saz
Svirala
Tar (Lute)
Triangle (Musical instrument)
Viola d'arame Portuguese viola
Violin
Yaogu Chinese temple drum, flower drum
Yue qin Moon lute, Chinese lute, Moon violin
Zūrnā Surna
Appendix C: Index to Song Transcriptions in English and Portuguese (Box 5)
Note: Song titles in parenthesis are alternate titles identified by Robertson
English Language Song Transcriptions by Title, A-Y
A-Cutting Down the Pine [musical transcription, lyrics]
A-Nutting We Will Go [musical transcription, lyrics]
Alonzo the Brave [musical transcription, 2 versions of lyrics]
As I Walked Out One Morning [musical transcription, 2 versions of lyrics]
As the Dew Flies over the Green Valley; see Wife Wrapped in Wether's Skin
Banks of Glencoe; see The Maid of Glencoe
Barbara Allen (Barb'ry Allen) [4 musical transcriptions, 4 versions of lyrics]
Barney McShane [lyrics]
The Beauty Bride; see I Courted a Fair Maid
Beneath the Old Oak Tree (Betsy) [musical transcription, 2 versions of lyrics]
Betsy; see Beneath the Old Oak Tree
Billy Boy [lyrics]
Billy Taylor; see Willie Taylor
Bingen on the Rhine
Bishop of Canterbury (King John)
Blue Julietta
The Boston Burglar
Brennan on the Moor; see The Cumberland's Crew
The Brave Solid
The Bridge Water; see The Bridgewater
The Bridgewater (The Bridge Water)
Brother Jack; see My Mother was a Lady
Buffalo buffalo (Death of McKinley)
Buried in Dirt
The Butcher Boy
The Candy Girl and Margy
Captain Hull and proud Dacus (Proud Dacus and Captain Hull); see John Brown
Captain Wedderburn's Courtship; see Many questions
Casey Jones
Chief Bright Sky
The Coast of La Barbaree; see Down around the Coast of Les Barbarees
Cole Younger
The Crooked Song
The Cruel Hiss
The Creole Girl; see Lake Ponsey Train
The Cumberland crew; see The Cumberland's Crew
The Cumberland's crew (Brennan on the Moor; The Cumberland Crew; The Sinking of the Cumberland)
Custer's Last Charge
Cutting Down the Pine; see A-Cutting Down the Pine
Dan Riley (Don Riley)
Dardanella; see Sleep, Baby, Sleep and Dardanella
The Dark Eyed Sailor (TheLousy miner)
The Days of Forty-Nine
Dear Adel, My Son
Death of McKinley; see Buffalo, Buffalo
The Devil Out of Hell (Scolding Wife)
Dogs: An Old Barbary Coast Song
Don Riley; see Dan Riley
Down around the Coast of La Barbaree; see Down around the Coast of Les Barbarees
Down around the Coast of Les Barbarees (The Coast of La Barbaree; Down around the Coast of La Barbaree; High Barbaree)
Down in the Diving Bell; see The Mermaid
The Dying Californian
The Fair Captive
Fair Charlotte (Young Charlotte)
Fanny More; see Henry the shepherd
First She Would and Then She Wouldn't Or, O, You Naughty, Naughty Man!
The Flying Cloud
Foreman Monroe; see Jam on Gerry's Rock
Fuller and Warren
A Garden Hymn for Easter
A Garland of Old Fashioned Roses
Georgie
Glencoe; see The maid of Glencoe
Goin' Down This Road Feelin' Bad; see Goin' Down That Road Feelin' Bad
Goin' Down That Road Feelin' Bad I Ain't Gonna Be Treated This A-Way; I'm Goin' Down This Road Feelin' Bad)
The Green Fields of Virginia
The Green Vallee
Greenhorn Bill
The Hampshire Bite; see Oxford Merchant
Hard times in Kansas
Hear the Nightingales Sing
Henry the Shepherd (Fanny More; Randal the Haughty)
Her Sweet Sailor Boy
Hieland Mary
High Barbaree; see Down around the Coast of Les Barbarees
The House Carpenter
I Ain't Gonna Be Treated This A-Way; see Goin' Down That Road Feelin' Bad
I'm Glad My Wife's in Europe
I'm Goin' Down This Road; see Goin' Down That Road Feelin' Bad
I Courted a Fair Maid
I Was Cast on Board to Serve My King; see I Was Forced on Board to Serve My King
I Was Forced on Board to Serve My King
India's Burning Sands
Irish-American Rag
It Ain't Gonna Rain No More (Taint Go'in To Rain No More)
It's Hard Times for the Girls
It Was Just before the Last Fierce Charge; see The Last Fierce Charge
Ivan Rue
Jack Donohue (The Wild Colonial Boy)
Jack Stafford
Jackets So Blue
Jam on Gerry's Rock (Foreman Monroe; Young Monroe)
Jennie Fair, John, Sweet Rosemary; see Wife Wrapped in Wether's Skin
Jinnie Jenkins (Oh, Will You Wear Red?; Will You Wear Red?)
John Brown
Johnnie's Been on Sea; see Johnny
Johnny (Johnnie's Been on Sea; Young Johnnie; Young Johnnie the Sailor)
Keith and Hiles Line
The Keyhole in the Door
King John; see Bishop of Canterbury
Kitty Wells
The Lady del Roy; see Lady Leroy
Lady Leroy (The Lady del Roy)
Lady Mary and Sir William; see Sir William and Lady Mary
Lake Ponchartrain; see Lake Ponsey Train
Lake Ponsey Train (The Creole Girl; Lake Ponchartrain)
Lally-tu-dum (Lolly Tu Dum; Rally Trudum; Rolly Trudum)
Lamanda
The Lass of Glen Shee
The Lass of Mohee; see The Little Mohee
The Last Fierce Charge (It Was Just before the Last Fierce Charge; Twas Just before the Last Fierce Charge)
The Little Brown Bulls
Little Matty Grove; see Mathy Grove
The Little Mohee (The Lass of Mohee)
Lolly tu dum; see Lally-tu-dum
Lord Bakeman (Lord Bateman; The Turkish lady; Young Beichan)
Lord Bateman; see Lord Bakeman
Lord Thomas and Fair Ellender
The Lousy Miner; see Dark-Eyed Sailor
Love Henry; see The well water
Lowlands of Holland
The lyre bird and the jay
MacDonald of Glencoe; see The Maid of Glencoe
Madam, I Have Come A-Courting (An Old Quaker Dialogue; O, Madam, I Have Come A-Courting)
The Maid of Glencoe (Banks of Glencoe; Glencoe; MacDonald of Glencoe)
A Maiden in her Garden Walking (The soldier's bride)
Margy; see The Candy Girl and Margy
Mary of the Wild Moor; see The Wind that Sweeps o'er the Wild Moor
Mathie Groves; see Mathy Grove
Mathy Grove (Mathy Groves; Mathie Groves; Little Matty Grove)
Mathy Groves; see Mathy Grove
The Mermaid (Down in the Diving Bell)
The Milwaukee Fire
Molly Dear
Molly Melancholy
The Mormon-Eyed Preacher
The Motor Car Mamma
Moses
The Mowing of the Hay
My Father and Mother were Irish
My Mother and Father Were Irish; see My Father and Mother Were Irish
My Gal Sal
My Mother Was a Lady (Brother Jack)
Narragansett Bay
O, Madam, I Have Come A-Courting; see Madam, I Have Come A-Courting
Oh, She Licked Him and She Kicked Him
Oh, They Told Me Out in Kansas
Oh, Will You Wear Red?; see Jinnie Jenkins
Old England's Shores
Old Ned Moore
An Old Quaker Dialogue; see Madam, I Have Come A-Courting
Old Sam Finley Had a Pig
On Cloddie's Banks
Our Goodman (Putting on the Agony)
Overalls in Mrs. Murphy's Chowder (Who Threw the Overalls in Mrs. Murphy's Chowder?)
Oxford Merchant (The Hampshire Bite)
The Peanut Stand
Pompey Smith
Popularity
The Prisoner's Song (with answer)
Proud Dacus and Captain Hull; see Captain Hull and Proud Dacus
Putting on the Agony; see Our Goodman
The Quaker Courtship (The Quaker's Courtship)
The Rake and Rambling Blade (So I Robbed Old Nelse)
Rally Trudum; see Lally-Tu-Dum
Randal the Haughty; see Henry the Shepherd
Rolly Trudum; see Lally-Tu-Dum
Root, Hog, or Die
The Rose
Sally the Queen
Sam Bass
Sandy Far at Sea
Sargeant Tally-Ho (Sergeant Tally-Ho)
Scolding Wife; see The Devil Out of Hell
Sergeant Tally-Ho; see Sargeant Tally-Ho
The Shanty Boy
She Wore a Yellow Ribbon
The Sinking of the Cumberland; see The Cumberland's Crew
Sir William and Lady Mary
Sleep, Baby, Sleep and Dardanella (Dardanella)
Snooky-Oo-Kums (Snooky-Vo-Kums)
Snooky-Vo-Kums; see Snooky-Oo-Kums
So I Robbed Old Nelse; see The Rake and Rambling Blade
The Soldier's Bride; see A Maiden in Her Garden Walking
The Soldier's Sweetheart
Sterling's Hotel (Stirling's Hotel)
Stirling's Hotel; see Sterling's Hotel
The Stone That Goes Rolling Will Gather No Moss (The Stone That Keeps Rolling Will Gather No Moss)
The Stone That Keeps Rolling Will Gather No Moss; see The Stone That Goes Rolling Will Gather No Moss
Sweet Jane
Sweet Mary, Weep No More for Me; see When Mary Laid Her Down to Sleep
Swingtime in Springtime; see Popularity
The Tailor Boy
Taint Go'in to Rain No More; see It Ain't Gonna Rain No More
Texas Canyon
Tib, the Gray Mare; see Young Johnny the Miller
True Lover of Mine
The Turkish Lady; see Lord Bakeman
Twas Just before the Last Fierce Charge; see The Last Fierce Charge
The Unconstant Lover
Uncle Sam is Rich Enough
Virginia
The Wars of Santa Fe
The Weeping Willow
The Well Water (Love Henry; Young Henry)
We're Building Bridges
When Mary Laid Her Down to Sleep (Sweet Mary, Weep No More for Me)
White Pine Mine
Wife Wrapped in Wether's Skin (As the Dew Flies Over the Green Valley; Jennie Fair, John, Sweet Rosemary)
Who Threw the Overalls in Mrs. Murphy's Chowder?; see Overalls in Mrs. Murphy's Chowder
The Wild Colonial Boy; see Jack Donohue
Will You Wear Red?; see Jinnie Jenkins
William Riley; see Willie Riley
Willie Riley
Willie Riley and His Dear Coolin Bawn; see Willie Riley
Willie Taylor (Billy Taylor; William Taylor)
The Wind That Sweeps o'er the Wild Moor (Mary of the Wild Moor)
Young Beichan; see Lord Bakeman
Young Charlotte; see Fair Charlotte
Young Henry; see The Well Water
Young Johnnie; see Johnny
Young Johnny the Miller (Tib, the Gray Mare)
Young Johnny the Sailor; see Johnny
Young Man Who Would Not Hoe Corn
Young Monroe; see Jam on Gerry's Rock
Appendix D: Portuguese Language Song Transcriptions by Title, A-V
A Beira d'Alvo Regalo
As Carvoeiras
Adeus Ulina
A Florista
Ai-Ai-Amor
Balance
Coradinha; see A Coradinha
Escolha Par
Fado de Coimbra
Fado dos Passarinhos
Fado Corrido
Fado Hilario
Fado Minha Mai
Ha Chum
Lydia
Margarida
Mariana Costureira
Minha Mai
Minha Mai E' Pobresinha
Noite de Natal
O Carvalho Milagroso
Oh Laurentina
Oh Minha Mai [Oh My Mother]; see Fado Minha Mai
Oh Senhor Ladrao [Oh Mister Robber]
Ora Vai Tu
Padeirinha [Little Baker Girl]
Ru-Chu-Chu
San Joao [Saint John]
Santos Reis [Wise Men]
Sao Joao [St. John]
Tia Anica [Aunt Anica]
Triste Fado
Tyrolando
Vira do Minho [The Vira of Minho] (Folk Dance)